Welcome everybody. I'm very happy to pick up where Marvin left off last week. I'm Jonathan
and I have the distinct pleasure to today tell you about how to scale Gaussian processes
to large data sets. And what we'll see today is that we'll use a lot of the tools that
we've developed last week. In particular, last week we talked about the textbook way
to solve linear systems using the Tulaski decomposition and we applied that to 2P regression.
Today to give you context where we are in the course, today we're essentially developing
the modern way to solve such linear systems with kernel matrices and apply that to scale
Gaussian processes. And then next week we'll give you the probabilistic numerics interpretation.
So how do I learn about the machines that I use to build learning machines? So next week
we'll be the learning machines view. Today we'll be kind of the preparation for that.
Now I'll start to use language that interprets these numerical methods as learning methods
as well. Alright, so today GPs on large data sets will do that by using iterative methods
to solve linear systems. We'll see in particular that these methods can be viewed as learning
algorithms for the matrix inverse which is the primary object that we need to compute
the GP posterior. And then we'll develop a method to do quadratic time as opposed to
cubic time inference for GPs. And finally at the very end I'll give you kind of a hint
at that you can actually do this faster in linear time in the size of the data set but
that might come with some drawbacks and then we'll talk more about that next lecture.
Okay, so now that we've situated us, please during the lecture at any point if you don't
understand anything just ask me, I'll do my best to answer and with that let's get into
it. Okay, quick recap about Gaussian processes. Talked about them last week a little bit.
Why do we kind of focus on them as a base case so much? So the main goal for regression
is we are trying to learn an unknown function in this case f star from a training data set
of examples, right? Kind of the basic example of regression and what do we want from our
model if you do regression? Ideally maybe the most important thing is we wanted to generalize
to data that we do not have in our training to the set. But there might be some other
goals as well alongside this generalization goal. So second of all, we might want our
model to be sufficiently simple or interpretable that we can actually understand what's going
on after training, what the model has actually learned. Then third, we really would also
like to know how much to trust the prediction, right? If you just get a point estimate, we
might be not actually sure how much we should trust in that point estimate is that a good
prediction far away from the data. And then finally, we really want this to be fast, right?
It doesn't help us if our model trains for, let's say, 300 days, then we can't use that
really well in practice. And GPs are really kind of the prime example where we can hit
all of these points. So for example, of course you want generalization that's just what we
need for regression, but then GPs in some way are simple and interpretable because we
can reason about what the kernel kind of encodes, what assumptions about the data. We get an
uncertainty estimate that tells us how much we should trust the prediction, assuming our
model is correct. And then finally, as we learned last week, it's actually very expensive
to train them and do inference, right? So what do we do about that last point? And that's
what we'll deal with today. Alright, so just as a reminder, this is what the Gaussian process
posterior looks like in the mean. We have kind of an error term between the data and our prior
mean, our prior prediction that gets scaled by the inverse of the Gram matrix. You can think of
that as how strict should I interpret this error? So if my uncertainty, my prior uncertainty is
very large, maybe it's fine if I'm far away from the true data, right? But if my uncertainty is
actually very concentrated, I should make a big update to be closer to the training data. And
then the covariance evaluated at data points also involves this inversion of a matrix of the size
of the data set. Now really, GPU regression actually is two parts, right? It's not just
computing the posterior. We also need to find the kernel hyperparameters. So do model selection
in a way. So this would be your training loop during deep learning, for example. And the loss that
we optimize for GPs is the log marginal likelihood. So given this kernel hyperparameter or these
kernel hyperparameters, how likely is it that the data were generated from this model? And you can
see that if we underfit, for example, here the length scale of the model is actually much wider
than the true length scale that generated the data in black from the true function in gray dashed
versus the opposite end of the spectrum here, our length scale of the kernel. So the distance in
which we assume data points to be related is much too short and we kind of overfit, right? We should
expect to be actually, as we move away from a training data point very quickly, our model says
we don't actually know anything about where the true function was. Okay, so those are the two
tasks. And last week, we talked about the Juleski decomposition. So this is a reminder of the
Juleski decomposition. Sorry, for GPU regression, what we need is we need to do linear solves with
this Gramian size of the data set, the kernel matrix plus a noise. And we need to do that both
for the posterior mean and then for the covariance as well, depending on how many data points we
evaluate at here and data points. And then for model selection, we need the log determinant. We
just saw that right here, the complexity term, kind of a regularization. And then we also need
its gradient if you do gradient based hyperparameter optimization to find the hyperparameters. And last
week, we developed that you can use a Juleski decomposition for this, right? Is this great
problem solved, right? Does everything compute the log determinant, computes linear solves? Perfect.
Here's an illustration of that. On the left, we have a kernel matrix. I believe this is a
Matern 3 half kernel. And you get these Juleski factors, L and L transpose. Now, just as a quick
aside, kernel matrices don't always look this nicely ordered, right? This is the one dimensional
data set where the data is actually, you can order the data just from smallest value to largest
value. But in general, for high dimensional data sets, or if your data set is just not ordered,
the kernel matrix doesn't necessarily look the structured because the correlation between
two data points depends on their distance. And two data points that I order next to each other
don't have to be proximal in input space. Okay. But here's a big issue with the Juleski decomposition.
And you might have seen that in the homework already. I asked you to use your GP implementation
to train on a large data set, 100,000 data points, and you should have probably found this,
depending on your system, right? You're not going to be able to form even form that kernel matrix
in memory because it takes about 80 gigabytes. So maybe you have a very, very big machine with
a lot of RAM and you have 80 gigabytes of RAM, then you'll probably still face this problem.
A modern CPU, excuse me, has about one gigaflop per second. So 10 to the nine floating point
operations per second. If we plug that into the number of operations we need for the Juleski
decomposition, one over three times n cubed, random size of the data set, it'll take you about
83 hours to do that, more than a little overhead. Okay. That's kind of not acceptable.
Later in the lecture, I'll show you what I did this morning. You can do this in seven and a half
minutes to desirable accuracy. Okay. So clearly the Juleski decomposition is prohibitive both in
time and space for large data sets that we might care about. What can we do instead? We'll talk about
iterative methods today and we'll try to reduce the complexity to squared in the number of data
points. You've already seen this as well. This is again the Juleski decomposition and now I only
show a couple of columns in the low rank, sorry, a couple of columns in the Juleski factor which
gives me a low rank approximation for the kernel matrix. If I do I iterations of the Juleski
in its iterative form, that's a rank I matrix. But that's not really what we need for GP regression,
right? We need an approximation to the inverse, not the kernel matrix itself. So is there a way
that we can also interpret the iterative formulation of the Juleski where we stop it early
as an approximation to the precision matrix is another name for the inverse of the kernel matrix.
Can we do this, right? Can we approximate the linear solves here,
down here, with the inverse Gramian which is I plotted here somehow by a matrix that's called
CI such that somehow if I apply the matrix CI to a some vector that this is close to the linear
solve with the kernel matrix. All right, let's take a closer look at this iterative form of the
Juleski decomposition on the left here that we've seen last time. So just as a reminder,
we put in a symmetric positive definite matrix A, in our case that's just the kernel matrix plus
the noise. And we get out a lower triangular factor and if we stop it after I iterations,
that only has I columns that are non-zero. And then we get an approximation to the kernel matrix.
So what happens here? So really there's only two things going on kind of down here.
A prime is sort of like the residual, the part of the kernel matrix that we haven't learned.
You can see that by you can reformulate that as just A minus the current approximation of the matrix
Li times Li transpose. So this is kind of a matrix residual, let's call it.
And then there's a second thing going on where as Marvin developed last week,
this step here, you can interpret as multiplying this residual with a vector,
in this case the unit vector up to scaling that selects a data point of the kernel matrix. That
just selects a column of the matrix. And depending on how you choose these, you might get a worse or
better approximation after I iterations less than N. Okay, now can we kind of rewrite this
algorithm by tracking a few more quantities to also get an inverse approximation out of this?
First, our goal is to find such a Ci, an inverse approximation,
and we know we have this matrix approximation Li times Li transpose. Can we somehow kind of
wrangle our algorithm to also get an inverse approximation? And what we could do, for example,
if I just take this equation and I multiply from the left and right with A inverse,
right, then obviously on the right side I have A inverse here, and on the left side I have my
Cholesky factors that I multiply from the left with A inverse. Now that didn't really get me
much because I'm trying to solve or I'm trying to invert the matrix A, so if to get an approximation
for the inverse, I need the inverse itself that doesn't really solve the problem, but let's see
what actually the entries of this matrix look like. So clearly the Ci is actually a low rank
matrix, right, because Li and Li transpose are both only have i columns, and the last column
is just A inverse times this Li vector that we constructed in step seven, and we just put into
the next column of the Cholesky factor. Okay, so if I just evaluate or just plug in the formula for
Li, which is just A prime times this scaled unit vector, remember A prime is kind of the residual,
the thing that we haven't learned about A, and I plug in my definition for the residual, right,
that's the matrix itself minus the part that I've learned in the last iteration,
and then I multiply A inverse into this, so I get an identity matrix here, that's what you can see
here, and then I get A inverse times Li minus one, and then I can also just introduce an identity
matrix on the right hand side by adding A inverse times A, okay, and now what I have in here is
just A inverse times Li minus one times A inverse times Li minus one transposed, but that's just
the inverse approximation from the previous iteration, so now I've reduced this last column
of this Cholesky factor to something that I computed in the previous iteration, so I can
recursively also construct the inverse approximation, and that inverse approximation is actually also
low rank in the same way that I construct the low rank approximation to the matrix A, okay,
so really the Cholesky is actually also an approximate matrix inversion algorithm,
okay, so now I added some terms into this Cholesky to kind of show what we need to track
to compute this inverse approximation as well, so first of all, we select a unit vector that
corresponds to selecting a data point if we do, if A is a kernel matrix, and let's call that action,
then I do a bunch of stuff, and let's focus on the bottom party first, so you've seen that
here we update the matrix residual, and now I've found a way to also compute this
approximation to the inverse Ci, okay, and by definition of Ci we said it was A inverse times Li,
A inverse times Li transpose, I can rewrite this update also in terms of Ci, and what we'll find
is that if I just, you know, take out A out of this, of these parentheses, I just get A times
A inverse minus Ci times A, so in here is the residual for the inverse matrix, in the same way
that out here, right, I have A minus some low rank factor, low rank approximation, in here I have A
inverse minus some low rank approximation of inverse, so hidden in here is kind of this, this
residual, and then if I multiply A in from the right I get this I minus Ci A factor,
and now that pops up again up here in the algorithm, so I modify my action a little bit
with this factor here, and then I multiply with this modified vector Di with the matrix A, and if
I do that what I essentially do is take this residual matrix, right, A times this factor
times the unit vector EI, so that's the observation that you previously did in Scholesky, let's take
a step back, that's this right, residual times EI, question? So for us, sorry, for us residual is
the thing that we care about minus our approximation, okay, all right, so we have a way to
modify our action to get some vector D, and it turns out that this inverse approximation is just
at each iteration I add an outer product of these vectors Di, okay, and we see that down here as well,
right, now this I minus Ci minus 1 times A times EI just gets replaced by the vector Di,
and let's do a quick complexity analysis, is that actually more expensive than doing the
Scholesky by itself? We know that the Scholesky periteration takes over n squared, and let's take
a look at the actions, at the kind of computations that we added, okay, so here we have a matrix
vector multiplication and another matrix vector multiplication that's still n squared, in this
eta I normalization constant step, we also just do matrix vector multiplication, and then down here
this is a low-rank matrix, so we can actually just track the low-rank factors by saving,
storing the Di's, or even if we multiply this out with an outer product, this is also just over
n squared, okay, so periteration you just pay n squared to do this, so asymptotically it's just
as expensive as if we just approximated the matrix itself, all right, let's take a look at what
this looks like if you apply to Gaussian process regression, so remember for just computing the
posterior we need these two matrix inverses of the kernel matrix size n by n, now we have an
approximation to this inverse, so what happens if you just replace that with this inverse approximation?
We get this, so this is three iterations of the partial Cholesky, partial because we don't
run it to convergence, and the data points that we selected or the unit vectors for our actions
are just selecting the data points in blue here, so in sequence from the left to right the first
three, now clearly not the greatest approximation, right, like basically back here we haven't learned
anything about the true function in gray dashed, now you might notice also that this
kind of looks like GPU regression if you only did GPU regression on the first three data points,
right, and in fact doing the partial Cholesky with no noise is equivalent to GPU regression
if you're, and you're selecting the data points that your pivoting strategy selects,
so your unit vectors, and if you add noise it's almost the same not quite, okay, so you can think
of the partial Cholesky as something like doing GPU regression but conditioning only on a few data
points, so last time we already saw that it really matters what pivots you choose or in other language
what unit vectors you choose, what data points you select, right, it's just all names for the
different thing, all the same, all different names for the same thing, and it turns out that
here that's also the case, so on the left I just chose, I think this is 10 iterations
of the partial Cholesky, and as unit vectors as actions I chose those actions that selected
the first 10 data points on the left here, and you can see that in this region myogliol
have learned the true posterior mean in black quite well, all the way over here we essentially
have learned nothing about the true posterior that we're trying to approximate, now on the right
I just chose a random order for the actions, so a random selection of data points that I
consider a random selection of columns of the kernel matrix that I look at in the partial
Cholesky, and you can see that this looks much better, right, the posterior is much closer to
the true posterior in dashed and black lines, and also you can imagine that we've learned quite a
lot more about the function and we're much more certain about where it is, so this choice of data
points not only matters for approximating the kernel matrix, in particular it also matters if
you approximate the inverse and thus for GP approximation, okay, so you can think of this
selection of actions, the selection of unit vectors for the Cholesky as a kind of act of learning,
in the sense that if I had a strategy that while I do this at each iteration picks kind of better
data points to condition on, I can actually learn much faster as is exemplified here by the random
order, but you could also think of a different strategy that selects data points in a smarter
way, and we'll see that later, okay, so the selection of data points that you choose really
matters for how quickly you converge to this inverse approximation and thus to the GP posterior,
so how do we do this smarter, can we find better actions to do this,
so on the left there's another illustration of this, so inside the partial Cholesky there's a step
where we take the residual a prime, so the thing that we haven't, or the part of the matrix that
we haven't learned yet, that we can rewrite via this, so via this part where we correct our action
with the inverse approximation from the previous step, and this looks like this, so this is the
residual after also ten iterations of the partial Cholesky, and every time I select, I chose a unit
vector that selects one of these data points, and you can see that most of the data points here have
been selected, the ones here and the ones down here, I think those are maybe 30 data points or
something like that, so in each step I choose a data point and the residual of the matrix look like
this, but why do I have to restrict myself to a vector that looks like this, the operation,
the cooperation cost per iteration is squared in the number of data points anyways, so I can
afford a matrix vector multiplication here, I can choose any vector, I don't have to select a column,
so what if we found a better vector with some different entries, maybe even more than one,
to more quickly approximate the kernel matrix or the inverse, which we just learned is kind of the
same, and here I chose some strategy that I'm going to tell you about in a moment, and clearly,
just visually, you can see that it's more close to the true matrix, the true kernel matrix,
so what's a better way, more efficient way, to choose these actions?
Okay, so this is the second part of the talk, and we'll talk about a method called the method of
conjugate gradients that's originally been designed to solve linear systems as they pop up, for example,
in GP regression, with symmetric positive definite matrices, kernel matrices are symmetric positive
definite, so that's great, and now we'll dive in kind of a little bit to the classic view of
how this method works, and then I'll pull you back into this view of actually learning about
the matrix, or learning about the inverse as we've already seen, okay, so method of conjugate
gradients. Our goal is to solve a linear system AX equals B, so A you can always just think of as
a kernel matrix for our purposes, and you want to do that with ideally very few matrix vector
multiplies, so just a few quadratic cost operations on the size of the dataset to quickly approximate
the posterior. Now, a different way of thinking about this problem AX equals B, where A is a
matrix and B is a vector of size n, you can rephrase this as a quadratic optimization problem,
and let me show you how that works, so take this quadratic function, where the argument X is a
vector of size n, if you take its gradient, then setting the gradient to zero, so solving this,
or optimizing this quadratic, which is a convex optimization problem, so as a global minimum,
is actually equivalent to solving the linear system AX equals B, okay, so taking the gradient
of this, just this AX minus B, setting it to zero means the equivalent to AX equals B,
and now I can also define something, another residual here, which is B minus AX, so if I
plug in something for X, that tells me how well I've solved the system, or equivalently is my
current negative gradient of this system, okay, so it points in the direction of steepest descent,
so what's your favorite optimization algorithm, just shout it out,
nobody has a favorite optimization algorithm,
all right, so what if you just throw gradient descent at this problem, right, why not,
gradient descent is super easy, we can compute the gradient, it's just B minus AX for the
current position X, why don't we do gradient descent, all right, so here on the right in blue,
these contour lines are the acupotential lines, so at which the function has the same value,
so the blue contour lines are the function f of X, the minimum, so the solution is here, X,
which is equivalently the minimizer of this function, and as we just learned,
the solution to this linear system, so if I do gradient descent, I follow the direction of steepest
descent, what I get is the green line here, so I start at X zero here, the direction, the green
line is orthogonal to the acupotential lines, take one step, and I can actually minimize
the one-dimensional quadratic along this distance in closed form, so I land here, right, if I
step any further, I would actually increase my function value again, so that's great, and then
I do it a bunch of times, so one, two, three, four, five, maybe six times, six steps, fine, right,
so one observation here, these gradient steps for this quadratic are always orthogonal to each
other in the Euclidean inner product, okay, can I do any better? Anybody have any ideas?
What if I slightly modify the directions that I walk in, not to be orthogonal with respect to the
Euclidean inner product, so the inner product that induces the two norm, but that are orthogonal
with respect to the A norm, where A is our matrix, okay, what does that look like? So here in red,
we have one example of this, I take one step, and then the next step is orthogonal in the geometry
that's induced by these blue lines, so what does that mean? Imagine you could squish this
landscape, this blue landscape such that the blue lines are actually a circle, okay,
you could squish everything, in this squished space, what the red path does is it takes right
angle steps, okay, now of course we don't have the squished kind of space, we have this elongated
space, so in this elongated space, taking orthogonal steps, it actually seems to be a fine idea,
but takes six steps, versus if I take right angle steps in the squished space, it seems to be just
take two steps, and that's actually a general result that you can show here, that if you follow
such conjugate directions, let's call them conjugate being another word for orthogonal
in an arbitrary inner product, perfect in an arbitrary inner product, I can converge in at
most n steps, and now let's do a slight modification of this, because for the first step we don't have
decided yet where we should go, right, we can go in any direction, why don't we just take
our gradient, negative gradient as a first step, walk into the direction of steepest descent,
and then just modify our steps always to satisfy this conjugacy condition, for which we then know
we can actually converge for these two-dimensional problems in exactly two steps, in
exact arithmetic, okay, so that's the idea, and this is what the algorithm looks like, so
don't get too intimidated by all the symbols, I just want you to kind of get the gist of what
the individual steps do in this graphic, okay, so I'm just going to explain kind of the high-level
parts of this, and it's not super important to know exactly how to derive these steps, we'll
do that next lecture in a more general form, so my algorithm gets a matrix A, a vector B,
and an initial guess for the solution x0, I have some stopping criterion, for example,
based on the gradient, right, the gradient norm, if that's zero, we're at the end here,
and then in the beginning I compute the residual, which we just learned is just a negative gradient,
right, so I compute the steepest descent direction, then to actually figure out in which
look, in which direction I should search, in which direction I should walk, called search
direction, I take my negative gradient, step ri minus one, and then I do some correction,
and that correction in this case depends on the previous step, so that's the intuition that
when I take a gradient step in green here, and I can't take the next gradient step, I have to
slightly correct it for what I've done previously, okay, so that's this correction part here, this
minus, depending on the previous search direction, and then finally, based on the search direction,
I can update my estimate for the solution with some step length, and the step length
is the exact minimizer along this direction, and you can see here, by the acupotential lines,
if I would walk farther, I would actually increase the function value again, okay, so this is the
minimum along this direction, all right, so this is the method of conjugate gradients, great,
but remember, we're looking for a method that approximates the inverse,
because we don't only have to solve one linear system for the mean, but also multiple ones
for the posterior covariance, right, because we have this right hand side is a kernel evaluated
at the training data set and new data points, okay, so can we also do the same thing or similar
thing as we did for the partial Scholaski by interpreting this CG method as one that also
constructs an approximation to the inverse, and the answer is yes, of course, otherwise,
I wouldn't be telling you, so now we also want a matrix CI that approximates the inverse
from this method, and we'll see that this is also low rank in the same way that it was low rank
for the partial Scholaski, and in black, I just carried over the steps and maybe slightly
reformulated them, so let's take a look at that, so here for the search direction, sorry,
in the beginning, I compute the residual again, same thing, and then I just call that residual
my action, okay, SI, and now correcting this residual as we did here turns out we can write as
just the residual itself minus the correction that depends on the previous inverse approximation,
okay, so this term here that looks very complicated can rewrite with the same structure as we had
for the partial Scholaski, that's the conjugacy correction, and it turns out that the, this
search direction, if we take the outer product up to scaling and sum that up, that turns out to be
this inverse approximation, and to give you an intuition, sort of a very high-level intuition
of why that works, so if I take this form of the approximation of the inverse, and I multiply
the right-hand side vector B, right, up here, it kind of should make, or if this was consistent,
this inverse approximation with my solution estimate XI, it should be the case that if I
multiply CI, the inverse approximation with B, I should get XI, right, otherwise I'm actually
sort of developing two different estimates for the solution of this linear system,
so it only makes sense if the CI actually is equal to XI if I multiply it with the right-hand side,
because it's an approximation to the inverse, so now we know that the update for the solution
estimate involves this conjugate direction DI, right, that's the update up to scaling,
so this matrix CI here, if that is to make sense, has to,
or if it's low-rank, has to have the form all previous search directions stacked into columns
times all the vectors stacked into rows, because then I get a linear combination
of these search directions DI as updates here, and that's exactly the form that we see here,
we get one DI times row vector DI transposed per iteration, so I realize that that's a lot to take
in, but it's actually not so important to understand where this comes from, because we're doing that
next week, but think of what I want you to get is this intuition here, okay, I can select actions
that actually solve this linear system very quickly, and we'll see that in a moment,
okay, quick comparison to the partial Sholesky that we saw before, you'll recognize now a bunch of
things here, right, here we selected a unit vector as an action, here we're selecting the residual
or negative gradient, here we're slightly modifying our action, doing the same thing over here for
the residual to get the search direction, we're estimating an inverse here with a low-rank,
actually rank one update, same thing over here, now of course for the Sholesky we didn't actually
solve a specific linear system, so we didn't have a step where we estimate a solution,
but actually we could compute the solution here as well by doing the same thing, multiplying
the inverse approximation with the right hand side, okay, so these algorithms are actually very
similar, we just typically understand them from very different angles, okay, so let's compare
them for GP inference, so we just again replace the kernel matrix inverse with this CI the inverse
approximation, and on the left here we have the partial Sholesky for tenor durations with
randomly sampled data points, you can see that now where we pick data points the uncertainty is
contracted, and here is conjugate gradient which automatically we don't even have to specify what
data points to pick because of this residual action strategy, actually is much more contracted
and matches the true posterior and black dashed lines and the true posterior mean and black much
better, right, the red is our approximation, the black is what we want, so this intuitively kind
of shows that the method of conjugate gradient seems to converge much much faster, and why like
what is this interpretation of this these actions, so the actions you can think of as probing the
matrix that we care about that we want to invert in a certain way, and however you structure that
action probes the matrix in a different way, so here for this GP approximation we kind of probe
at this point, then we probe at this point, then we probe at this point, and then at this point,
and the GP approximation contracts around for CG our residual vector in general probes were our
estimate of the posterior mean is still far away from the data set, so it probes globally at every
single data point in general and scaled with how far away I am from the data point, that's exactly
what the residual is, if you take a look back here it's for GPs it's the data B is a data Y
minus the kernel matrix times the representables, so that's the intuition why this works so well
for GPs, so notice I'm already using terms that you might know from kind of other machine learning
courses, action in terms of deciding where to evaluate or where to observe,
learning about the inverse matrix, and we'll see a lot more of this language later, okay, so we saw that
apologies, there we go, so we kind of intuitively or based on this picture it seems like the method
of conjugate gradients converges much faster, but actually how fast does it converge, right,
and now I have to take a quick numerics interlude to actually analyze this,
for those of you that haven't been in contact with numerics too much here's a quick slide for the
three most important concepts from your numerics lecture, I hope I'm not stepping on anybody's
toes here, so the first one is machine precision, whenever we're working on a computer and not just
in abstract mathematics there's unavoidable rounding error because I can only store my
numbers on my machine up to a certain precision, so I call that here just the floating point
rounding error fl of some theoretical quantity x that I can store on my machine as x tilde,
now whenever I have such a distortion on my disk and I apply some operation to it, for example
solve a linear system and I store my matrix and my right hand side on my computer,
those are suddenly slightly distorted potentially, and if I apply the exact algorithm for inversion,
so the theoretical mathematical operation that inverts that matrix, I still have unavoidable
error that gets introduced, right, because my inputs are slightly distorted, so also my outputs
get distorted, this bigger white circle here, and one way to measure this unavoidable error
amplification through the mathematical operation that I'm trying to implement in an algorithm,
for the case of solving the new systems, that is called the condition number,
so it's technically it's unavoidable relative error amplification, but you can think of it as
just unavoidable error amplification, and that turns out to be the maximum, the largest eigenvalue
divided by the smallest eigenvalue in absolute terms, okay, so kind of the, if you think of
the matrix representing a quadratic function as we had just a few slides ago, here the blue lines,
in this case, how elongated this quadratic is in its largest elongation direction divided by its
smallest elongation direction, sorry, the other way around, smallest divided by largest,
but it's the largest eigenvalue divided by smallest, okay, and then there's a second
quantity and this is just as a service, now what happens if I actually try to implement
this theoretical mathematical operation in an algorithm, I've had like the conjugate gradient
method or the Cholesky, then there's additional error coming from this implementation, maybe
doing a rounding in between, or just not being true to the true mathematical operation, and if
then my error is not too large, not too far away from this unavoidable amplification, I call that
stability, okay, now for example the Cholesky is a stable algorithm, so if you solve a linear
system on your computer with a Cholesky decomposition, the error you should expect is on the order of
the condition number depending on what norm you measured in, okay, so if that's really large,
no algorithm in the world is going to be able to solve that linear system to machine precision,
machine precision, so double precision is roughly 10 to the minus 16, okay, so if my condition
number is 10 to the 16, good luck finding an algorithm that's going to solve that linear system
to some precision that you desired that's smaller than one, okay, all right, so now we can analyze
the convergence behavior of the method of conjugate gradients, here on the left here I have a system
with a kernel matrix that has a thousand data points and has a moderately large condition
number, 10 to the 5, and in the x-axis I have the number of iterations I run for CG, and on the y-axis
I have the error in a norm, so that's the true solution of the linear system minus my approximation
in a norm, and it turns out that, so first of all let's observe that we can't actually reach the
double machine precision accuracy at roughly 10 to the minus 16 because our condition number is
pretty large, now it's not exactly that we can just add, you know, five orders of magnitude to this
because technically this is in two norm and this is in a norm, but certainly we cannot reach 10 to
the minus 16 here, when it turns out for this method of conjugate gradients the convergence
rate, so how quickly it converges to the true solution is given by this condition number
of the matrix A, by the largest divided by the smallest eigenvalue to some power i, so if A is
very close to one, does this converge fast or slow?
If A is close, sorry, if the condition number of A is close to one, does this term decrease fast
with i or slow with i? What is the numerator if kappa of i is close to one? Just shout it out.
Close to zero, okay, what about the denominator?
Close to two, so this is almost what? So if now I take that to a power, does that decrease fast or slow?
Compared to if, let's say kappa of A is a million, what is the fraction here, roughly?
Almost one, so what converges faster if kappa is a million or if kappa is one?
One, right? Because then this thing here is almost zero, so this arrow decreases really fast, okay?
Because if this is a million, then this is almost one, and if it's one, it doesn't decrease at all.
So the closer to one we are, the slower we converge. So here, I should expect actually not such fast
convergence, right? The condition number is quite large. Turns out it converges still quite okay in
a few hundred iterations relative to the problem size, a thousand, that's not too bad. By the way,
I only chose such a small problem here because I actually need to compute the true solution
to evaluate this, right? So I need to be able to compute a Chulaski to get a solution that's
within unavoidable error. So we can see that CG converges fast if the condition number of my
system is small. But does that mean it converges fast for all cases that we care about, for example,
for the kernel matrices? Here, similar example, a thousand data points, A is a kernel matrix,
and I vary the damping for the observation noise of my model. I increase it from red to blue,
sorry, I decrease it from red to blue, so I assume less and less noise in my observations.
And you can see that the convergence of CG actually slows down as I decrease the observation
noise. And the reason is, let's take a look. Here's the kernel matrix, k plus sigma squared i,
k is an SPD matrix, or at least symmetric positive semi-definite because it's a kernel matrix. So we
can do an eigen decomposition where q are the eigenvectors and lambda is a diagonal matrix
with the eigenvalues on the diagonal. Now we can find an eigen decomposition where q
has orthogonal eigenvectors, actually often normal eigenvectors. So I can just introduce
an identity matrix here, q times q transposes identity. And I can pull in the sigma squared i
to actually find the eigenvalues of k plus sigma squared i. And they are the eigenvalues of k,
lambda is a diagonal matrix with the eigenvalues, where each eigenvalue gets a sigma squared added
to it. So now if I want to compute the condition number of this kernel matrix in the beginning,
I just need the largest eigenvalue of the kernel matrix, sorry, if this damped kernel
matrix in the beginning, I just need the largest eigenvalue of the kernel matrix without damping
plus the damping. And now you can see what happens if I
take sigma squared to be very, very small. What happens if I take sigma squared to zero
to what does this term converge? Just shout.
Take this term, let sigma squared go to zero. What does it converge to?
Just the condition number of k, right, lambda max of k divided by lambda min of k. It turns out
that for most kernels, these are very, very different numbers. Such matrices are very,
very badly conditioned. So lambda max is much larger than lambda min. So if I increase sigma
squared, the opposite happens, right? In the extreme case, if I let that go to infinity,
then this converges to one. Obviously, then I assume that I have very large observation noise,
so I don't learn anything about my problem. So this is kind of tradeoff going on.
The more noise I assume, the easier my numerical problem gets,
but the less I actually learn about the function that I'm trying to learn.
And to give you an intuition why this condition number of k is large,
the condition number is something like the largest eigenvalue divided by the smallest
eigenvalue. Now, if I have two data points in my dataset that are the same,
two rows in my kernel matrix are the same, right? Because the row of a kernel matrix are
the kernel evaluated at the current data point and all other data points. So if I have two rows,
where I have the same data points, I just have the same rows. And obviously, then that matrix has
a zero eigenvalue, low rank, right? Doesn't have, sorry, has rank less than n. And if it has
rank less than n, then this eigenvalue has to be zero. So as data points get closer to each other,
the condition number of a kernel matrix blows up and close to each other is relative to the
kernel length scale. So if observation noise is small, so sigma squared, let's say is very close to
zero and I have close data points in input space, I have a problem because then CG converges slowly.
So what can we do about this? The answer to this is preconditioning. So assume we have a
computational tractable approximation P to the matrix A. So we know something about this matrix,
in this case, the kernel matrix. And we assume that the storing this matrix is rather cheap
relative to storing the matrix A. We can actually efficiently evaluate its inverse,
or pseudo inverse, and maybe we even know it's determined. So we know a lot about this
matrix that's approximately A. And the idea is we solve an equivalent linear system where we
just multiply from the left with P inverse. And this system still has the same solution x, right?
I haven't changed anything except that I multiply from the left, but this equation still holds.
So x is still a solution to the linear system P inverse A as a matrix and P inverse B at the
right-hand side. And now if I can choose my preconditioner such that this condition number is
much, much, much smaller than the condition of the original matrix, I've gained a lot, right?
Because I've replaced my original problem with an easier to solve problem where my method CG
converges much faster. And the intuition you should have about this preconditioner is it's
like prior knowledge about my problem. I sort of know something about this system that I'm trying
to solve that makes it easier for me to solve in the same way that I'll say I take a probabilistic
learning method if my prior is very concentrated around the true quantity that I'm trying to infer,
I can learn very quickly or I don't have to actually collect a lot of data. And preconditioning is
the same intuition. And geometrically what preconditioning does is this is a 2D linear system
again with interpretation as an optimization of a quadratic where blue lines are the counter lines
and I have a large eigenvalue and a small eigenvalue. That's why it's kind of elongated.
Now if I have a, if my precondition is just the inverse itself, it immediately snaps the matrix
A to an identity matrix. And I don't have to do anything because it just says x equals P inverse
B and I have a solution. So P kind of transforms my problem in such a way that it's slightly
closer to the identity matrix and then easy to solve. And it turns out that because of this property
here that the condition of the system gets lowered, it actually accelerates CG. And in final precision
actually makes it also more stable but we won't go into that. Okay, so let's try to get an intuition
for how we can use this form of prior information. And I use that term loosely next next time we'll
make it precise to quickly excel to solve linear systems quickly for GP regression. Okay, so if I
now use CG with a precondition, it's actually very simple. The only thing I have to change is
I don't look into the direction of steepest descent r i minus one, so the residual or
negative gradient, but I slightly warp that based on this precondition. And what happens is here's
again number of iterations of CG in log space and the error in a norm to the true solution.
As I increase the quality of my precondition right here, I'll explain the type of precondition
in a moment, you can see that I actually converge faster, right? The error decreases and this is
in log space, so I need a factor two orders of, sorry, more order of magnitude fewer iterations
for this problem is again a kernel matrix. How do we get such a preconditioner? Well, we can actually
use the partial Scholesky that we already introduced here. So one way to precondition
kernel matrices is to approximately approximate the kernel matrix K at the noise and then this
is a low rank approximation of rank L, right? I just run the partial Scholesky for a few iterations
and then I can store this thing in, it's just L vectors of size n, so it's O of nL which is
cheap compared to the size of the matrix. And this is a low rank plus diagonal preconditioner,
so as you learned last week, you can invert it via the matrix inversion lemma.
Okay, so you can also compute the inverse, p inverse here very quickly and last week we learned
that's O of nL squared, so even linear time and we can afford quadratic time for iteration.
So that's also the precondition that we used up here. Yeah.
It's true, you have that, so you could even construct an even better preconditioner
by selecting better data points. Very true. But it turns out even, you know, doing a very
dumb strategy just randomly sampling really accelerates my method. And the issue is if
I would just run CG without preconditioning, it doesn't converge as fast because of the
convergence statement. Okay, so somehow that's a really good method but we have to warm start it
maybe a little bit to get that benefit. That's kind of the intuition. Okay, so now let's try that
out. Here's a large-scale linear solve and I promised you in the very beginning that I'm gonna
reduce the time of 83 hours of solving a large-scale linear system with 100,000 data points
to about seven minutes. Here's such a data set, matrix of size 100,000. This is a kernel matrix,
is a maternal 3 half kernel. I use a preconditioner, I run it, departs Cholesky for 20 iterations,
that takes about one and a half minutes on my machine upstairs. And then I run the precondition
Cholesky. And what you see is that the residual converges to about 10 to the minus 8, 10 to the
minus 9 in 60 iterations. Okay, so actually we could have stopped this even earlier maybe in about
three minutes and would have gotten a very accurate solution. Now one quick side note,
I'm not showing the error in A norm here because I would have to compute the exact solution but I
can't do that because the system is too large. Right, so I can only show you the residual norm
but that's the proxy that we use to track how accurate we are. And the residual norm is almost
the same thing as the error in A norm, it's the error in A transpose A norm. Okay, so you can see
that, I can now do, I can compute a GP posterior for a 100,000 data point data set in maybe seven
minutes on my desktop machine upstairs. Now you might ask, well I have to do more than one solve,
right, I have to maybe during hyper parameter optimization do multiple solves. Actually,
you might be able to reuse preconditioners for this or if you actually have multiple systems
then you need to solve this cost also on mortises because you only have to compute the
preconditioner once. Okay, but what about hyper parameter optimization? I've only told you how
to solve linear systems, I haven't told you anything about how we actually do hyper parameter
optimization. Portulowski, Mavin told you they can just compute the log determinant by taking the
product of the diagonal of the lower triangular factor. How do we do this for CG?
We need to, remember, we need one optimize, we want to find parameters theta of the kernel
like the length scale to optimize the log marginal likelihood that's our loss or objective function.
So we need to evaluate the loss to kind of check how good we are and most importantly we need to
compute its gradient so we can actually optimize with a gradient based optimizer. So it turns out
the gradient of the log marginal likelihood here remember it has a fit term here that involves
a linear system solve and a log determinant. If I take the gradient with respect to the
hyper parameters I get this term for the fit so that's again two linear system solves
with the data and a trace term here as the derivative of the log determinant of the kernel
matrix that also involves a linear system solve. So we have two costly operations to do this
hyper parameter optimization. We need to solve linear systems, k hat inverse times a vector,
most of the time it's the data minus our prior mean and in this case it's also a linear system
solved with the derivative of the kernel matrix but we solved this. We can use CG, that seems to
be really fast, we have to precondition fine but actually we can scale that up to as you just saw
100,000 data points. But what do we do about these things? We also have to compute traces.
Arguably maybe we could say we can get away with not evaluating the log marginal likelihood and just
terminate when our gradients are vanishing right maybe that's fine but that still involves the
trace of a linear system solve. Now how do we compute these traces?
Let's take a step back and look at the definition. So the trace of a matrix is the sum of its diagonal
okay so the sum over the diagonal elements aii one way I could write this using matrix vector
multiplication is just multiply from the left and right with unit vectors that select the diagonal
element right. Actually it's also equivalent to the sum of the eigenvalues but this is the thing
that we want to look at for now. But our problem is we can't afford cubic computation, we can't afford
n matrix vector multiplies because that would be n times n squared cubic. We want to ideally
approximate this thing to high accuracy with l much fewer than n matrix vector multiplies because
if we can do that we can solve the near systems with small number of iterations i and we can
compute traces with a small number of iterations l and hopefully i plus l is much smaller than n
then we found a method that approximates gush process regression in quadratic time
on very large scale data sets as we just saw. So let's make an observation about this trace of
a matrix. Say we had an orthogonal matrix z so that c times z transposed is just the identity
matrix then we can just rewrite the trace of a as the trace of a times its identity matrix
we're just introducing a one and by trace rotation i can just pull this matrix to the front
and i get the trace of z transpose az and if i just use the definition of the trace as selecting
kind of the diagonal elements what i get is it's selecting z i transpose az i or i get terms that
are z i transpose az i and that's also actually the proof for this being the sum of the eigenvalues
because if you choose often normal eigenvectors for this you just get back the eigenvalues right
because a z i if z i is an eigenvector is lambda i times the eigenvector and z i transpose z i is
just one because it's an orthonormal system okay but that still doesn't get it get us all the way
there because that's still n actually two n matrix sorry n matrix vector multiplications okay crap
well what do we do if we don't know what to do why don't we just randomize why don't we just draw
a small number of random vectors with a certain distribution in this case zero mean and covariance
such that if i scale it with the square root of the dimension i get the identity covariance
maybe i can hope that that's actually a good approximation of this thing up here and let's
see whether that works the trace of a i again can introduce just an identity matrix now i
posit that the covariance of square root of n times z i equals the identity identity then this
square root of n gets squared and pulled out traces linear i get an n up here and the trace of a times
the covariance of z i but the covariance of z i is nothing but the expected value of its square
for vectors that z i times z i transpose minus the squared of the expectation but the expectation is
zero so i just get the first term here and now i can pull out sorry i can pull in since the expectation
is linear my matrix a so i get a times z i z i transpose i can flip the expectation and the
trace because they're both linear and i can do trace rotation to pull up the z i transpose to the
front so they get the trace of a scalar now and of that the expectation now the trace of a scalar
is just the scalar itself so n times the expectation of this quadratic form z i transpose a z i and
now i can approximate this expectation with Monte Carlo so i only draw l random vectors
to get an approximation of this trace that's the idea the intuition you can take from up here
right if i just choose a bunch of z i maybe that's already a good approximation to the trace
and that's the idea of this randomized approximation so now i found a way to also reduce this problem
of trace estimation to matrix vector multiplication which is the operation that i know is quadratic
time i can really do really fast on the computer and hopefully i only need a small number of these
random vectors but i don't need a small number of random vectors here is a plot that shows the
number of random vectors on the x-axis for the estimation of the log determinant now remember
last time you saw that you can rewrite the log determinant as a trace i'll show you that again
one second here the log determinant of the kernel matrix you can rewrite as the trace
of the matrix logarithm of the kernel matrix so if i could evaluate the logarithm of the
kernel matrix i could just do this trace estimation strategy that we just outlined
let's assume we can just compute this function of a kernel matrix for us it's always
the log if you care about the log determinant and not care so much that we also have to estimate
this in the middle let's just say we can do that and what you'll find is here if i look at the number
of random vectors that i take for my Monte Carlo estimate the estimate for the log determinant
that i get through the stochastic trace estimate actually has a lot of variance at the beginning
right you can see that i'm qualitatively pretty far away from the true value in gray dashed
that i want to estimate and i literally need tens of thousands of random vectors
and this is actually a problem of size 10 000 so i found a strategy to solve my issue problem
that is just as expensive as Cholesky which i can't do on large datasets so crap right what do i do
well this is a property of Monte Carlo estimators that they just converge at this rather slow
speed one over the square root of the number of random vectors or random samples this is going
to be an issue because it really slows down my hyper parameter optimization and i just simply
can't afford to do that so what can you do you can again use something that we already know
we have a preconditioner for our linear system solve so we know something about
approximately how the kernel matrix looks like and it's inverse can we use that to solve this
issue here you can do that by if you look at the log determinant you can introduce a one
identity matrix by just producing the preconditioner you can think of a partial Cholesky here if you
want and it's inverse and then using the rules of the matrix logarithm i can pull out this log
determinant of the preconditioner and we assume that that was known right so we have some part
about this log determinant k hat that we already know and then i get a residual here again that's
something like you know the trace of the difference between the matrix logarithms
and you can already see that if the preconditioner p hat gets close to k hat this term becomes very
insignificant right and my log determinant of of the preconditioner is very close to the true log
determinant so the strategy is use the part that you've not that we know our prior information
pull it out and estimate this trace back here via the stochastic trace estimate
and we can do that and what we'll find if you do that is that the estimator converges much much
quicker literally a difference between tens of random vectors and tens of thousands of random
vectors to reach a qualitatively similar level and that's the same kind of behavior you expect
from cg right if you have a good preconditioner you convert much much faster as we saw previously
but turns out you can also use the same information that you have about the matrix also for this
trace estimation
now for the gradient of the log determinant you can do the same thing you just differentiate
once through this thing and all the quantities that you need are available for example through
automatic differentiation if you have a if you implement this and let's say pi torch
and you recover and this is not super important you recover the same rate at which the preconditioner
approach of the kernel matrix for this estimate to get a speed up and qualitatively you see this
here right you tends to 100 random vectors is what we need to get the same error level
and this is how g pi torch which is the most popular library in pi tor python for gashu
processes works internally so it uses cg if you just use a vanilla exact gashu process from g pi
torch uses cg to compute the linear system solves precondition cg and then it uses this preconditioned
log determinant estimation and derivative of the log determinant estimation to do hyper parameter
optimization and with that you can scale to data sets these are all data sets on the x axis from
the UCI machine learning repository i think some of them are not but they have data set data set
sizes between 25 000 and a million data points here and now this is on a gpu because even matrix
vector multiplies get significantly difficult if um your system is just large enough but you can
paralyze them easily so with these strategies that we just showed you you can you know within
about an hour train on a data set with roughly 250 280 000 data points and up to a day for a
million data points if you have gpu's available okay and internally that works exactly how i just
showed you now just to give you a notice about what pretraining and not pretraining is pretraining is
just sample a small data set of the data set that you're training on to get hyper parameters that are
approximately good and then start from there start optimizing from there
yeah
so so the question was can i explain again how essentially this part right why do we get this
increase in the rate so clearly if the preconditioner if it's a low rank preconditioner it depends on
the rank l of the low rank part if that gets close to k hat this part goes to zero right
but to actually figure out how good our estimate is turns out this contribution depends on how
quickly the preconditioner converges to the kernel matrix yeah could imagine that you need to take a
lot of pre computation to get a good estimate of the kernel matrix then that would not help you very
much because it's very costly to do that if this thing converges very very quickly to the kernel
matrix you can invest very small amount of pre computation to do this variance reduction strategy
to this quicker convergence strategy okay and it turns out that if typically you know something
about how fast your preconditioner converges and you inherit this rate specifically also for the
Monte Carlo estimate so instead of one over square root of the number of random vectors you converge
with a speedup that's polynomial sometimes even exponential and what that means is you know
you converge to the true value much much much faster
okay so now you know how you can do this large scale with iterative approaches
you can scale Gaussian processes to large data sets let's do a quick
recap and of observations before we move to the final part so you've seen that we kind of used
language of iterative solvers choose these things called actions which are vectors that essentially
determine how to observe my matrix my kernel matrix in our case this choice of how to observe
the kernel matrix through the matrix vector multiply really affects how fast we converge
okay you saw that because cg which used the different strategies used residual vectors
converge much much faster in just a few steps relative to the problem size which was
a hundred thousand for the example that I showed we had about what's 60 80 iterations
now choosing these actions can kind of be interpreted as the solver choosing itself what
to observe about the numerical problem in this case solving the linear system
problem and we know that if you if you put in more information about our problem if you already know
an approximate inverse of the matrix through a preconditioner we can accelerate these methods
either for linear system solve like for cg or for this precondition log determinant estimation
through this stochastic trace system so in conclusion for these to develop fast numerical
algorithms for these for the Gaussian process case you really need some sort of domain expertise
in the sense that these solvers need to know something about the problem that they're solving
through the precondition ideally or through the choice of actions to quickly converge if you just
do naively part of Cholesky you saw that that didn't really look like the g posterior if you
just selected the data points in order so the algorithms themselves need to know something
about the problem to converge fast but we can tell them how to collect that information to
warm start themselves but can we do this even faster I said now we have a method that uses a
small number of quadratic operations matrix vector multiplies to scale to large data sets
but can we do this even faster in linear time in the size of the data set so
our inference method scales not with the problem size for the power of two but just with the problem
size itself so this idea is actually a little bit older than the iterative methods approach
not the specific idea but the idea of linear time gp inference and I'll show you kind of the most
modern version of it and here again this is just to give you a kind of a slight quick overview we
won't go too deep into this so one observation you can make about any data set basically
specifically the low dimensional that the data points in them are often quite similar
that you often have data points that are quite redundant you get training examples where the
example that you get is similar to one that you've seen previously now wouldn't it be great
if we could compress that data into a smaller training data set let's call it inducing inputs
because it's induced from the training data that kind of summarizes the training data in a in a
way right so if I have a million data points what if I could find a hundred or a thousand
data points that just really well summarize the data that I have in my data set so the idea is
we can do this through something called variational approximation so we directly approximate the
posterior instead of using numerical algorithms to compute the mathematical operations in the
posterior okay so this is changing the model for your Gaussian process so you're not actually doing
gp regression anymore and approximating that but you're using a different model to get as close as
possible to the Gaussian process posterior and one way to do this is called stochastic
variational Gaussian processes and what they do is they posit a different Gaussian process
that depends on z these inducing inputs the summary of the training data and the posterior here
looks very similar to the one you know for gps right so let's ignore this correction term for a
moment then this part here looks like gp regression without noise on these inducing inputs because we
have kernel function evaluated new data points and then here kernel matrix evaluated all the
inducing inputs inverted times something and for the kernel we have prior kernel minus an update
term that again involves something that is the kernel matrix evaluated at the inducing inputs
inverted so if we had no noise this looks almost like standard gp regression just on the inducing
inputs now it turns out that for this to be kind of smart you actually have a correction term and
you can already think about that actually the observation noise pops up nowhere here right
so how does that enter turns out it enters here so there are two more parameters of this term one is
the vector mu here and then this correction term kind of dampens the adds more uncertainty
so i have three things that i can modify to get a good approximation to my Gaussian process posterior
that is the summary of the training data this vector mu here that plays a role like the
observations the label vector and a term that adds additional uncertainty through sigma here
and what we can do is we can evaluate the KL divergence which is the statistical distance
between the approximation and the true gp posterior and we can do that
to optimize the summary of the training data the vector that represents kind of our observations
at z and this additional uncertainty term that corrects for that we are only looking at a small
data set a small summary data set and we can do this in o of i squared n and
sorry i lost the moff pointer
and let's take a look at how this comes about
so in black you can see that we have to invert the kernel matrix at the inducing inputs
we only have i inducing inputs a small number maybe a thousand instead of a hundred thousand
data points so this inverse is really cheap because it's only of size i by i
any other terms that we find in there are just
evaluating the kernel matrix at these i data points and then maybe at the training
data set during training okay so all the operations that we need are either i cubed
or i squared times n because n is the size of the training data
so
where the one exception is evaluating with the one exception being
evaluating the kernel matrix at the entire training to set but that doesn't pop up during
optimization of this so the idea is summarize the training data find a direct approximation
to the posterior and that direct approximation only takes o of i squared n
great right should we forget about iterative methods now
so there's different ways you can do this the the the reason for the naming stochastic here
is typically you do something like batched optimization or sgd so you can really quickly
optimize this with your favorite optimizer typically
so the most expensive operation is asymptotically in this but there's you know a number of optimization
steps that you do but the most expensive operation in the training data set size is n okay
remember for iterative methods we also have to do a hyper parameter optimization so we also have
to solve multiple problems that create a complexity for one for each hyper parameter optimization
step but the number of hyper parameter optimization steps is typically way way way smaller than the
problem size okay so great right now i spent maybe an hour telling you about iterative methods and
now i'm telling you you shouldn't use them well this is what happens
for example if you do stochastic variational Gaussian processes so here in blue is the exact
gp on this small data set so that we can visualize it in black x's are the observations so these are
our training data in blue light blue is the uncertainty of the exact gp
and in gray lines here are the inducing inputs so this is where we initialize our summary of the
training data set here's a summary to the point here here here here here and here and here now
during optimization i said we optimize both the mean as these parameters mu and and sigma
but also the inducing inputs and you can see here as i optimize here is where i start these
inducing inputs find a location that summarizes the data set well
but there's one issue if you look at the
uncertainty quantification away from the inducing the inputs it's very very different
from the true Gaussian process from the exact Gaussian process right and even where i have
inducing inputs my posterior mean doesn't necessarily approximate the true exact posterior mean well
now for iterative methods i haven't shown you such a i have shown you such plots but i have also
quantified how close it is right to the true solution so the question is is this a problem
for these linear time methods and how much of a problem is it for iterative methods the one thing
we have going for us with iterative methods is we can online
control the accuracy of our approximation right we can just keep running the method until we
have no more time and then stop and that's how accurate our gp approximation is the inducing
point method typically you have to set the number of inducing points a priority for your data set
and then you do you optimize them now you can run the optimizer for however long you want but
the number of inducing points take the same so you have to kind of control the fidelity of your
approximation before you start optimizing so but what if this is just way faster right
we saw that the the theoretical complexity is way faster and we see now this has an
issue with uncertainty quantification so the question that i leave you with today
is can we design a method where we can trust the uncertainty quantification
just as much doing any part of the approximation no matter how much computation we've done
whenever we stop can we trust the uncertainty here clearly we cannot trust the uncertainty
quantification of our method right it's way far away from the exact gp assuming our model is correct
all right with that i'll summarize
we've seen that clearly scaling Gaussian processes to large data sets requires approximation
they are memory and time complexity costs associated with it iterative methods like the
part of Cholesky CG enable us to approximate the posterior and do hyper parameter optimization
in quadratic time in the size of the data set there's also an interpretation of these methods
as active learning algorithms and we like that precise next time preconditioning is a way to
accelerate these methods and that's can be interpreted as a form of prior information
something i already know about the problem that i put in to make my method faster to learn faster
and then finally sparse gp approximations enable inference in linear time so way faster
but there might be an issue of uncertainty quantification right and really for gps that's
the entire point why we use Gaussian processes because we want to be you know want to know
how much we should trust our prediction okay so next week i'll actually make that precise
in what way are these iterative methods actually learning machines in what ways are the tools we
use to approximate learning algorithms like the Gaussian process learning algorithms in themselves
and i won't only use kind of language that alludes to that but i'll actually show you exactly
and with that i'll close today five minutes early so that's perfect for you to now fill out the
feedback form i very much appreciate that and if you have any questions raise your hand i'm happy
to answer anything to the best of my ability thank you